<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Newte's sermon concerning the lawfulness and use of organs in the Christian church</title>
            <author>Newte, John, 1655?-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11782078</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11782078</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49134</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52247)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49134)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 544:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Newte's sermon concerning the lawfulness and use of organs in the Christian church</title>
                  <author>Newte, John, 1655?-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Freeman Collins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CL, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Music in churches.</term>
               <term>Organ (Musical instrument) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49134:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49134:1"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>NEWTE</hi>'s SERMON Concerning the LAWFULNESS and USE OF ORGANS IN THE <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49134:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49134:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lawfulneſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Organs in the Chriſtian Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Aſſerted in A SERMON Preached at TIVERTON IN THE County of Devon Upon the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> 1696.</p>
            <p>On Occaſion of an ORGAN's being Erected in that Pariſh Church.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN NEWTE,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Rector of <hi>Tiverton</hi> in <hi>Devon;</hi> ſometime Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of <hi>Baliol</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Freeman Collins</hi> in the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>William Rogers</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet;</hi> and by <hi>Humphry Burton</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Tiverton.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49134:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49134:3"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>Right Reverend Father in GOD,</hi> JONATHAN <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> EXETER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE Have at laſt, with your Favour and Encouragement, Erected an Organ in our Pariſh Church A thing which I have almoſt theſe Ten years endeavoured to do; and had once obtained the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of it from your Lordſhip's worthy Predeceſſor, the late moſt Reverend Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> This ſeemed at that Time to be Embraced and Subſcribed to with great Affection by the whole Body of our Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; but the want of Sincerity in ſome, or a vigorous Proſecution in others, under the Everlaſting Pretence of the Badneſs of the Times, gave a Diſcouragement to the Deſign, however Uſeful and Beneficial it
<pb facs="tcp:49134:4"/>was. And ſo for that Time it came to No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>But now I hope our Tempers are chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the better, and that they are not ſo bad, as they may be Repreſented to be; which, our continual Averſion to this ſort of Church-Muſick, would give the World too great cauſe to Suſpect: We have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore taken the beſt Courſe to Remove ſuch a Suſpicion, and to ſhew, That we Reſolve with our utmoſt Zeal and Diligence and Sincerity to Serve God, according to the Methods of our Excellent Conſtitution, in his own Houſe of Prayer; and by the help of the Organ to raiſe our Affections and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite our Devotion thereto.</p>
            <p>This being the firſt Erected in your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Dioceſs (out of the City) ſince the Great Rebellion had deſtroyed the Uſe of them in many Places. I could not but judge it moſt proper to Dedicate this Diſcourſe, which was Preached to a very Numerous Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, at the Time our Organ was firſt made Uſe of, to your Name, under the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Influence of whoſe Government, we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy ſo much Safety and Defence in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49134:4"/>
            <p>The Subject indeed deſerves your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, while it already has your Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But the Blame of the Compoſition muſt lye at my own Door, and I have no mind to add to that by making an Apology for its Publication.</p>
            <p>I could not indeed well avoid the giving leave to ſome Friends to Tranſcribe a Copy who deſired it; unleſs, I ſhould ſeem to ſhrink from a Juſtification of what I delivered to them from the Pulpit, which I think too mean a Thing, both with Reſpect to the Dignity of my Office, and the Argument I have undertaken to defend. Therefore I choſe rather to Gratifie them this way, than to give them that Trouble, which I am ſure would make it leſs Anſwer their Expectation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi>
It is now highly to be wiſhed (if ſuch a Wiſh be not too great in our days) That all others who poſſeſs the ſame Station and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in our Church with <hi>You,</hi> were as zealous and hearty in Promoting the Intereſt, and Defending the Rights of its Conſtitution. It would make ſome of us happy beyond our Expectation, and others beyond their Deſign,
<pb facs="tcp:49134:5"/>if not againſt their Wills. Then we might ſee our Excellent Eſtabliſhment and <hi>Old Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> flouriſh in our Time, as they did in that of our Forefathers.</p>
            <p>May you ſtill go on with a Primitive Zeal and Courage to ſupport this beſt Part of Chriſtianity; For, if this be ever ſuffered to fall, we have too much reaſon to think, That little elfe but Anarchy and Confuſion, if not Atheiſm and Profaneneſs, will quickly follow. Paſt Experience of this will, I hope, ſufficiently forewarn us againſt future Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And that the former may never again be tried, nor conſequently the latter ever more be felt in our Land, is and ſhall be the conſtant Prayer and Endeavours of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Obedient and moſt Faithful Servant <hi>JO. NEWTE.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Tidcombe,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 24. 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49134:5"/>
            <head>THE LAWFULNESS and USE OF ORGANS IN THE <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM CL. 4. latter part.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Praiſe him with ſtringed Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Organs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHEN <hi>holy David,</hi> the great Pattern for Adoration and Praiſe, either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion of ſome ſignal Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance received at the Hands of God; or being moved with a more than ordinary Impulſe of the Spirit, to Laud and Magnifie his holy Name for the multitude of his Mercies.</p>
            <p>Or when he more ordinarily Addreſſed himſelf unto him in Publick Prayer and Thankſgiving, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king known his Requeſts, making Profeſſion of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49134:6"/>his Faith, complaining of the State of the Wicked; of the Malice of his Enemies; giving Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Pious, or Comfort to the Afflicted; and upon moſt other Occaſions incident to the State and Condition of Himſelf and People.</p>
            <p>He preſently compoſed a <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and ſent for the chief Prefect of his Choir, to ſit and prepare it to ſome Muſical Inſtrument, ſuitable to the Occaſion, to Elevate his Mind, and to Excite his Devotion.</p>
            <p>And when his Predeceſſor <hi>Saul</hi> was poſſeſſed with the <hi>Evil Spirit,</hi> the Royal Prophet having notice of it,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.23.</note> 
               <hi>Took an Harp and play'd with his hand.</hi> So the latter part of the Verſe ſays, <hi>Saul was refreſhed and was well; and the Evil Spirit departed from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Evil Spirit from the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Lapide <hi>in</hi> v. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> was thought to be a deep Melancholy, which oppreſſed his Spirits and diſcompoſed his Mind, and which might lye the heavier upon him, through the Inſtigation of the Devil, being moſt apt to work Miſchief upon me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy People, and to bring them into ſuch a kind of Diſtraction. The proper Cure of this, was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be, a ſeaſonable Application of Muſick. The force of which, when made by the skilful Hand of the inſpired Muſician, the Devil could not withſtand. But in ſpite of his Fomenting the Diſeaſe, <hi>Saul</hi>'s Mind was exhilerated, and his Melancholy driven away.</p>
            <p>It will not now be amiſs, I hope, if from ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Uſe and Power of Muſick, I take the ſame Method of the <hi>Pſalmist,</hi> in recommending to your Practice, the conſtant offering up your Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Praiſes unto Almighty God, in this his <hi>own Houſe of Prayer,</hi> and in order to the being more De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and Zealous in the Divine Worſhip and Service,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49134:6"/>according to the excellent Method of our Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Liturgy, if I recommend alſo the Uſe of Church-Muſick in order to your more Solemn, Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Affectionate Performance of it.</p>
            <p>This being moſt proper to raiſe our Affections, to chear up our Hearts, and to Invigorate, as well as to Regulate our Deſires; and likewiſe to drive away the <hi>Evil Spirit</hi> from us. I do not mean only ſuch an heavy and melancholy Spirit as <hi>Saul</hi>'s was, but a much worſe; and no doubt, both raiſed and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the Devil too, <hi>viz.</hi> The Spirit of Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Hatred, and Animoſity. The Spirit of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, of Envy, of Malice, of Revenge, and other ſuch diſorderly and miſchievous Paſſions, which this will be apt to drive from our Minds, and is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Remedy againſt.</p>
            <p>Thoſe great Ends, among many others, which I ſhall hereafter ſhew, being very likely to be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by this means, will abundantly compenſate for that Pious and Exemplary Beneficence we have ſhewn, in erecting this ſtately and magnificent Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of an <hi>Organ,</hi> now Dedicated to the Honour of God, the Service of his Church, and the Good of his People. By an happy Providence, is this again reſtored to that very Place, from whence the other, by Sacrilegious Hands, was ſometime ſince, pull'd down and deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>And I doubt not but thoſe who have ſo freely contributed towards it, will conclude their Money put to a very good Uſe, and that they'l find a great Satisfaction in it themſelves; and the greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, as they ſee the Benefit and Advantage of it, redound both to themſelves and others. And may the Bleſſing of God go along with it, and Deſcend
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49134:7"/>upon the Heads of thoſe particularly, who have been the Encouragers and Promoters of it.</p>
            <p>To which, if it may in any wiſe contribute, I ſhall make it the Buſineſs of this Day to Aſſert the Lawfulneſs, and Recommend the Uſe of it. And this I have choſen to do, from a Conſideration of theſe moſt expreſs words of the <hi>Pſalmist,</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, in the Concluſion of that Divine Collection of his, in this laſt <hi>Pſalm;</hi> which, by the Title it bears,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> is <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> or <hi>Praiſe ye the Lord.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he Exhorts All People to call upon the Lord, and to Praiſe him in his Sanctuary; and that with all kinds of Muſical Inſtruments, particularly <hi>with ſtring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones and Organs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may very well here take for granted, I ſuppoſe, that Praiſe is one of the moſt Delightful, as well as one of the moſt Neceſſary Duties, we are obliged to perform towards God. That 'tis of an Eternal Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation upon us; and which engages all People, at all Times and in all Places. And alſo, That we are to take the beſt Courſe, and make uſe of the beſt Means, where they may be had, with reſpect to thoſe Times and Places, to make this Duty moſt Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate and Ardent, conſidering our own Weakneſs and Indiſpoſition; and likewiſe moſt Solemn and Acceptable, with Reſpect to the Majeſty of God.</p>
            <p>This I am to ſhew may be by Muſical Inſtruments, and among them, <hi>The Organ,</hi> as being the greateſt help to this ſort of Devotion.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Stringed Inſtruments</hi> in this place,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lorinus</hi> in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Felix Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetan</hi> and others ſuppoſe is to be underſtood ſome ſorts of them, now unknown to us. But according to the Hebrew word<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Species Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti Muſici. (Semel extat) <hi>Buxtorf.</hi> in loc.</note>, it ſignifies ſuch a one as is compounded of many ſorts of Muſical Inſtruments,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49134:7"/>and contains much variety of Muſical Harmony and Melodious Sounds, like unto that of the <hi>Organ,</hi> now in uſe; but differs from it, in that they were to be play'd upon, without the help of Wind, which this is not.</p>
            <p>And 'tis further obſervable, that an <hi>Organ</hi> in the Original is derived from a Root, which ſignifies to <hi>Love with ardency and vehemence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Adamavit,</hi> Buxtorf.</note> It ſeeming ſo to expreſs the Nature of the Thing, whoſe uſe is to ſtir up the Affections of the Soul towards God, that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot but be in love with it.</p>
            <p>In treating of which I ſhall proceed after this method.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> I ſhall aſſert the Lawfulneſs of Muſick, both Vocal and Inſtrumental, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of the latter, in the Time of Divine Service, as well in the Chriſtian Church now, as in the Jewiſh Church heretofore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall ſhew the great Uſe and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I ſhall Anſwer the moſt material Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which the Adverſaries of Church-Muſick, have againſt this Practice. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I ſhall conclude the whole, with an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to you to ſtick heartily and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly to the performance of that Excellent Church-Service of ours, eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as being the fitteſt and beſt of any in the whole Chriſtian World, to anſwer the ends of our Holy Profeſſion, namely, to give us a peaceable and happy Life here, and to bring us to Heaven here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49134:8"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> And <hi>first,</hi> I am to Aſſert the Lawfulneſs of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, both Vocal and Inſtrumental, and particularly of the latter in the Time of Divine Service, as well in the Chriſtian Church now, as in the Jewiſh here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore.</p>
            <p>Towards the Proof of which, I ſhall draw ſome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, * From the Light of Nature and the Reaſon of the Thing. * From the Authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Inſtitution of <hi>David,</hi> conſequent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon. * From the Senſe of the Apoſtles in the New Teſtament. * From the Opinion and Practice of the Reformed Churches, both at home and abroad. And * particularly from the Judgment of the moſt Eminent Men among thoſe, who diſſent from our Church in other Matters.</p>
            <p>This I take to be ſufficient for the Proof of the Thing before us; after which, I preſume, its Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs cannot well be called in queſtion.</p>
            <p>§ 1. The Lawfulneſs of that cannot certainly, with any tolerable Reaſon, be denied, which all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges have Allowed and Approved of.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Chron. 15.16.25. 1. Eccluſ. 50.16, 17, 18.
<p>The High Prieſt taught the People to Praiſe God and Pray therewith. 2 Chro. 15.14.</p>
                  <p>It was uſed at making a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God.</p>
               </note> God's own People of old, made their Approaches unto the True God, in a Religious manner with the Solemnity of Muſick, as well, as the Heathen, to their falſe Gods. Both finding ſuch a Natural fitneſs in the Thing, as would be likely to Excite their Devotion, and make it the more acceptable. And therefore, this being the general Practice of all Nations, that we read of, ſeems to argue, ſuch a way of Worſhip to proceed from the Dictates of Natural Religion, which, Men were not ſo much Taught as Born to.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49134:8"/>
            <p>Hence we find from the Teſtimony of Scripture, That before the Law was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Invention of Muſick was ſo early, as to be in the Days of <hi>Lamech,</hi> the ſixth from <hi>Adam;</hi> his Son <hi>Jubal, was the Father of all ſuch as handle the Harp and the Organ,</hi> Gen. 4.21. <hi>i. e.</hi> He was the Author and Inventor of theſe. And in the Days of <hi>Job,</hi> who is thought to have lived before <hi>Moſes,</hi> thoſe Inſtruments of Muſick which ſerved to rejoyce and chear up Mens hearts at their Feaſts, <hi>Job</hi> 21.12. <hi>God thought fit to Conſecrate to a Religious <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, and made them Inſtruments of much Honour to his Church, and much Devotion to his People,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hickman</hi> Conc. in Pſal. 100. 1. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</note> or Directions made in this Caſe by <hi>David,</hi> there were Inſtruments of Muſick uſed, and a Song made upon a Religious Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; as appears by theſe two Inſtances, of <hi>Miriam</hi> the Siſter of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and of the Prophets who came to meet <hi>Saul.</hi> The former we read of <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20, 21. who Celebrated the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> was no leſs than a Propheteſs, and ſhe did it after this manner: <hi>She took a Timbrel in her hand, and all the Women went out after her, with Timbrels and Dances. And</hi> Miri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am <hi>anſwered them, Sing ye to the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed here, that they ſung to one another by turns, this famous <hi>Song of Moſes;</hi> the Men beginning, and the Women anſwering them; or elſe the Propriety of Speech would not ſo well hold, of <hi>Miriam</hi>'s <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The other Inſtance was after the Delivering of the Law, but before the Reign of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript Appointment of it, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.5. where <hi>the Company of Prophets</hi> (are met by <hi>Saul</hi>) <hi>coming down from the High Place, with a Pſaltery, and a Tabret, and a Pipe, and an Harp before them;</hi> while they Propheſied and ſang Praiſes unto God.</p>
            <p>If we look into the Practice of the Heathen World, we ſhall find Inſtances of the ſame kind. <hi>Homer,</hi> one of the ancienteſt Writers among them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond in loc.</note> mentions the <hi>Greeks</hi> uſage in Celebrating the Praiſes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49134:9"/>of their Gods, with an Harp. The <hi>Phrygians</hi> with a Drum. And the <hi>Egyptians</hi> with a Timbrel. So the Idol-Worſhip in the Eaſtern part of the World, mentioned by the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> was performed with all kinds of Muſical Inſtruments and Muſick.<note place="margin">Dan. 3.5.</note> And the Weſtern, or the <hi>Roman</hi> had Muſick a great Ingredient in their Religion, and erected a Colledge of <hi>Tibicines</hi> or Players upon Wind-Muſick, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed them with great Priviledges, for their Solemn Performances herein.</p>
            <p>§ 2. But this is nothing to the Endowments that were made by <hi>David</hi> upon the ſeveral Officers,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 25. Chap. 23.5.</note> which were concerned in its Performances both in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, and alſo the Temple.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>David</hi> being a King and a Prophet, could not only do this at that time, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Uſe of it in the time of the Meſſias, whoſe Type he was. Pſal. 45. &amp; 146.</note> He firſt gave the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment to it in the Jewiſh Church; and by the Aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, made ſuch Heavenly Compoſures, as not only ſupplied the Jews with the moſt Excellent Forms of Prayer and Praiſe, upon all Occaſions, befitting that State: But to whom all after Ages are beholding for their Inſtructions here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and for thoſe lofty Strains of Divine Eloquence, which have wonderfully improved the Devotions of the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>And 'tis from ſo great a Man,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.14.</note> as this, <hi>after God's own heart,</hi> as well as from the Reaſon and Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Thing, that we in a great meaſure owe, the Advantages of Vocal and Inſtrumental Muſick among us.</p>
            <p>The Light of Nature indeed has given great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in this Matter: But the Revelation of God to his Prophets, greater. Whereby Mankind in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral have been loudly called upon by holy <hi>David</hi> particularly, and a great part of it has heard the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49134:9"/>Voice of the Prophet, and made uſe of ſuch means, as have raiſed their Devotion to an higher pitch, than otherwiſe they could have done, and conſequently have <hi>made the Praiſes of God more abundantly glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This is done by the help of Artificial Songs and Inſtrumental Muſick, to ſupply the Defects, and to heighten the Performances of Corrupted Nature;<note place="margin">Pſal. 98.</note> and to aſſiſt in Repairing that Voice of Joy and Gladneſs in ſerving the Lord, which had been mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably broken by Diſobedience and Sin; and made in a great meaſure defective, and not ſo capable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to reach the Delights, and to attain the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of that bleſſed Imployment.</p>
            <p>This <hi>ſweet Pſalmist</hi> (or Singer) <hi>of Iſrael</hi> therefore,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.1.</note> with divers other Prophets, who were Inſpired be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him, for this purpoſe, as, <hi>Heman, and Aſaph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>and Jeduthun, and perhaps the Sons of Corah too,</hi> whom we read of among the Compilers and Singers of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Pſalms, introduced into the Church of God among the Jews, the Uſe of ſuch Inſtruments, as were thought fit by them, being ſo Divinely Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to raiſe the Spirit of Devotion among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to make them Celebrate the Praiſes of their Creator, in the moſt Solemn Manner,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.8.</note> and with the greateſt Alacrity and Exultation as could be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined; beſt becoming the Reaſon, and anſwering the End of the chiefeſt part of the Creation.</p>
            <p>And from thence we may Argue, If this was Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful under the Jewiſh State, why not under the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian? Have not Chriſtians ſometimes the ſame Deadneſs and Dulneſs, and Spiritual Indiſpoſition in the Service of God, which the Jews had, and which lack to be ſhaken off? Do not the Members
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49134:10"/>of the Chriſtian Church in the Performance of their Worſhip, labour under the ſame Defects of theſe ſorts? And conſequently, Do they not ſtand in need of ſome ſuch Helps and Aſſiſtances, to move their Affections, to raiſe their Devotion, to ſhake off their Drowſineſs, and to inſpire their Thoughts with Chearfulneſs and Zeal, with Love and Veneration, when they make their Addreſſes unto him, in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Thankſgiving? If they do, as 'tis too mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt they do; for that Reaſon, have they always had the proper, if not neceſſary Aſſiſtance of Church-Muſick among them.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Vocal</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">I might here mention the Hymns of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias,</hi> and of <hi>Simeon,</hi> Luke 1 and 2d Chapters. And what is ſaid, in the opinion of <hi>Socrates,</hi> concerning St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> (who was ſuppoſed to be the Child, which our Saviour took and ſet in the midſt before his Diſciples, when he ſaid <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.3. <hi>Except ye be converted, and become as little Children, ye ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>) That 'twas he who firſt brought the Alternate way of Singing into the Chriſtian Church, having learnt this from a Viſion of Angels, thereby concluding the better to ſtir up one anothers Affections, and coming nearer to the Heavenly Pattern, where the Seraphims cry one to another, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy Lord God of Hosts,</hi> Iſai. 6.3. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cr. Hiſt. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 8 Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s <hi>Companion to the Temple, Part</hi> 2. § 8. And of the famous St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who added moſt melodious and artificial Singing to the Divine Service, in the Church of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> whereof he was Biſhop; and this way among the reſt; which ſoon after was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated to others. He it was, who compoſed the moſt Seraphick Hymn, which is in the Church, called the <hi>Te De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m,</hi> in Honour of the Bleſſed Trinity; which noble Strains, 'tis thought, he received down by Tradition from the Compoſitions of the Apoſtles, or ſome other Primitive Chriſtians, who were inſpired with the Gift of Singing. And for that reaſon have we ſuch frequent mention made of their Singing to and Praiſing God, <hi>with Spiritual Songs and Hymns,</hi> in the firſt and pureſt Ages of Chriſtianity, when they were ſo unfortunate as to be under the ſevereſt Perſecution; And to that Infelicity alone we owe the want of Inſtrumental Muſick to help out and exalt their Devotion. And <hi>Pliny,</hi> giving an account to the Emperour <hi>Trajan,</hi> of the Chriſtians, ſays, <hi>Hanc fuiſſe ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam vel Culpae vel Erroris Chriſtianorum, quod eſſent ſoliti, ſtato die, ante Lucem convenire, Carmenque Chriſto, quaſi De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dicere ſecum Invicem,</hi> Lib. 10. Ep. 97. de Chriſtianis.
<p>It will be too tedious to mention what great things are ſpoken concerning the Singing among the firſt of Chriſtians, both by the Greek and Latin Fathers, St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil, Juſt. Martyr,</hi> St. <hi>Augustine, Tertullian,</hi> &amp;c. And that the grave and plain Tune to the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> now retained in our Cathedral Churches, was ſet by <hi>Gregory the Great,</hi> who flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed about the end of the Sixth Century; a man very diligent in regulating and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing all the Publick Offices of the Church, whom none of his Succeſſors ever e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualled, <hi>Platina de Vit. Pontif. Greg.</hi> 1.— many other Authorities are reckoned up by the Biſhop of <hi>Cork,</hi> in his <hi>Duty of Singing,</hi> &amp;c. And I know not, why I might not with them, mention the Authority of the Worthies of our own Age, the great Lights of the Engliſh Church, <hi>Hooker, Hammond,</hi> and others, who were men of as great Learning and Piety as they, and why not of as great Authority among us, concerning that other way of Singing, with the Inſtruments of Muſick, joyned to their Voices? If this be Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial, why not the other? and both be aboliſhed, or neither.</p>
               </note> from the very beginning of Chriſtianity the Apoſtles of our Lord, and the Primitive Chriſtians practiſing it themſelves, and recommended it to others.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49134:10"/>And <hi>Inſtrumental</hi> too, when it got Eſtabliſhment in the World, and had the Protection of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Emperours,</hi> being freed from the ſevere and laſting Perſecutions it lay under for above Three hundred years together. And then afterwards, through the Diſconſolateneſs of the Times which followed, it could not preſently appear with that Splendour, as to have all thoſe Ornaments and Advantages which might well belong to it.</p>
            <p>We may conclude therefore, That 'twas through the Neceſſity, and not the Choice of the Primitive Chriſtians, that ſo helpful a Thing as Inſtrumental Muſick in the Service of God, was not more early received into the Chriſtian Church. And the juſt<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prolectat Aures Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Mulcedo.</hi> S. Cypr. Epiſt. ad Donatum.
<p>Vide S. Baſil. Homil. in Pſ. 1.</p>
                  <p>S. Aug. <hi>variis in locis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Encomium</hi> they give of it, ſhews what was their Mind and Deſire about it, though they were not able to bring it to effect.</p>
            <p>§ 3. It is obſervable, That when the Apoſtle, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> recommends <hi>the uſe of Pſalms and Hymns,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.19. Col. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>and Spiritual Songs, and to ſinging and making Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in our Hearts to the Lord,</hi> Epheſ. 5.19. And St. <hi>James,</hi>
               <note place="margin">James 5.13.</note> when he ſpeaks of Singing in token of a Religious Joy, ſays, <hi>Is any merry, let him ſing Pſalms?</hi> By which, doubtleſs, they underſtood the <hi>Pſalms of David,</hi> which are uſed in the Jewiſh Church. And by ſinging them, in both thoſe places, it is to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49134:11"/>ſuppoſed,<note place="margin">Vide Criticos Guelpt. &amp; Grot. in Epheſ. 5.19.</note> they mean with Inſtruments of Muſick. And to make the Truth of this Obſervation the more manifeſt to you, it is plain they expreſs themſelves by words,<note place="margin">Pſalmus eſt in quo concinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do adhibetur Muſicum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum praeter Linguam. Hymnus est propriè Laudis Canticum, ſive alta Voce, ſive aliter Canatur. Oda non Laudes tantùm continet, ſed Paraneſes &amp; alia Argumenta, <hi>Calvinus in Col. 3.16.</hi>
               </note> which in the Original (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from whence, that Inſtrument called the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi>) ſignifie moſt properly, a ſinging with an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And a Reverend<note n="*" place="margin">Biſhop of <hi>Derry</hi>'s Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Inventions of men in the Worſhip of God, <hi>c.</hi> 1. § 1.</note> Prelate obſerves from hence, <q>If they had not approved the Jewiſh way of Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, which was with Inſtruments, they would not have uſed a word that imported it.</q> Nay, it is not to be doubted, but (that they, who took ſo much care for the Regulating and well Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the Church in after Ages) would have cautioned againſt it, if they thought it improper, and that Singing with Inſtruments, was not conſiſtent with the <hi>Spirit and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo.</hi> But the Lawfulneſs of this,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14, 15.</note> and that Singing <hi>with the Spirit and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo,</hi> is conſiſtent with Singing with Muſical Inſtruments, I ſhall further urge from the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> and the Analogy it has with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Songs and Heavenly Exultations in the Quire of Bleſſed Saints,<note place="margin">Rev. 14.2.</note> who are repreſented <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.2. <hi>As Harpers harping with their Harps: And having the Harps of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">15.2.</note> Chap. 15.2. <q>Which Places con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Publick Worſhip of God in the Church, The Joys of the Saints in Heaven and in Earth,<note place="margin">Baxter, Bullinger, Hammond.</note> and the Triumphant Rejoycings of Chriſtians, for the Victory over their Enemies,</q> according to the Judgment of ſome Expoſitors.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49134:11"/>
            <p>§ 4. And however meanly this way of <hi>making melody in our hearts unto the Lord,</hi> may be thought by ſome, it has been certainly of above a Thouſand years ſtanding in the Chriſtian Church; and been Received and Approved of by the Reformed, as well as as the Popiſh Churches (and therefore no part of<note n="†" place="margin">Thoſe that have gotten the Victory over the Beaſt, and over his Image, and over his Mark, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Name, ſtand on the Sea of Glaſs, having the Harps of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2.</note> Popery). From theſe latter, I draw no Preſident, any farther, than they agree with the Churches in the pureſt and beſt Times. And for the former, the Opinion of <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> and their Followers will bear me out, whoſe Judgments in this matter, I ſhall juſt mention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luther,</hi> ſpeaking of the Communion-Service, that it ought to be in the Mother Tongue, ſays,<note n="†" place="margin">Miſſam vernaculam opto magis quam promitto; quòd impar ſim huic Operi, quia Muſicam ſimul &amp; ſpiritum deſiderat. <hi>In vit. Lutheri. He laments the want of Poets and Muſicians to Compoſe and Sing Godly Songs.</hi> Poetae &amp; Muſici nobis deſunt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>I rather wiſh, than promiſe it, being not ſufficient for ſo great a Work, for it requires both Muſick and a Spirit.</q> It is plain from hence, what he meant, but becauſe of the troubleſome Times where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he lived, he could not effect it.</p>
            <p>But its Followers, it ſeems, who muſt be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have beſt underſtood their Teacher's meaning, have affected it. For, in a great part of <hi>Germany, Swedeland, Denmark, Switzerland,</hi> and part of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where his Doctrine is received, they have the Exerciſe of Vocal and Inſtrumental Muſick in the Worſhip of God, as we have; and where they have not this Advantage, 'tis reckoned more their Unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs than their Choice.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49134:12"/>
            <p>So likewiſe <hi>Calvin</hi> gives his Approbation of it, in ſome Places; but being a Man of intemperate Heat and Paſſion, is inconſiſtent with himſelf in others. I ſhall only mention one, which is his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on <hi>Amos</hi> 6.5. where he highly commends<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>David</hi> quum eſſet qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etus poſtquam defunctus or at omnibus peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis, potuit etiam ſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectare, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>David;</hi> That <q>whereas, being Muſical and a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Muſick, he might privately have delighted himſelf therewith, when he was now in Peace and Eaſe, and paſt all his Dangers:<note n="†" place="margin">Quum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>David</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicuerit Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſica Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ad Pietatis exercitium ut mentem ſuam ad Deum at tolleret; — ut ſcilicet reſonarent Laudes Dei in Templo, ut indè una cum aliis Piis ſeſe erigeret ad Pietatis Studium, <hi>Calv. in Amos c. 6. v. 5.</hi>
                  </note> yet he choſe rather Muſical Inſtruments to the Exerciſe of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, that he might thereby raiſe his Mind to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.—And that they ſounding the Praiſes of God in the Temple, he might Excite both himſelf and others to the Study of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Dutch</hi>
               <note n="|" place="margin">Where all Sects in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion may meet, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do.</note> 
               <hi>Churches,</hi> which moſtly follow him, have the Uſe of Organs very frequent among them, almoſt in every Church, where the People are of Ability to procure them.</p>
            <p>But though none of the Reformed Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad did uſe them at all, it is ſufficient that ours does, to juſtifie their Lawfulneſs, being by far the beſt part of the Reformation. Concerning which, omitting the Teſtimony of our own Eminent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, who may, by ſome People, be thought too partial, I will give you the Judgment of an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Man, and a Forreigner, I mean the Learned <hi>Iſaac</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Si me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectura non fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit totius Reformationis pars integerrima est in <hi>Anglia,</hi> ubi cum ſtudio veritatis, viget Studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Antiquitatis; <hi>Ad Clem. Salmaf. Ep. 40.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caſaubon:</hi> 
               <q>If my Judgment (ſaith he) does not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49134:12"/>fail me, the ſincereſt part of the Reformation is in <hi>England,</hi> where, together with the Study of Truth, flouriſheth alſo the Study of Antiquity.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And this truly was, and is the Deſign and Glory of our Church, That it Retains the Doctrine and Practice of the Primitive Church, while it throws off the Corruptions and Errours that were foiſted into it, in after times. It allows and maintains what is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Reaſon, Decency, and good Report, whereby God may be worſhipped among us in Spirit and Truth, with Beauty and Devotion.</p>
            <p>And for this Reaſon it Retains the Uſe of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans in her Divine Service, as well approving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Muſick to adorn, as to heighten her Devotion. This being the chiefeſt of them all, and of ſuch admirable Variety and Fulneſs, as in a manner contains all other Muſical Inſtruments what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. Having ſuch a grave <hi>Decorum</hi> with it, and ſuch a ſingular Capacity, as is beſt able to keep an whole Congregation in decent Modulation of Voice, for ſinging the Praiſes of God; and with due Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Heart, for the better offering up their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unto him, which are certainly very great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages in a Chriſtian Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>And therefore, I ſay, ſhe retains the Uſe of the Organ, but not as it were abſolutely neceſſary, or as if the Eſſence of the Church did conſiſt in it, and that there could be no Church without it: But only as to its <hi>Bene eſſe,</hi> it's flouriſhing eſtate; to which, with reſpect to the ſuitableneſs of the Times and uſefulneſs of the Thing, it does abundantly conduce. And God be thank'd, we do not ſtand ſingly in Defence of this Uſage; we have all, I mean all the beſt eſtabliſhed Churches in the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49134:13"/>World, to concur with us herein, who are of Ability to make ſo great a Proviſion, for the better carrying on the Worſhip of God in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of his People. And if we approve our ſelves to theſe, 'tis no matter if we diſregard the Novelty and Phantaſticalneſs of ſome ſingular Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and be concerned no otherwiſe than to Pity and Diſcountenance the groundleſs Cavils, unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Prejudices of any to the contrary.</p>
            <p>'Twas only through the Iniquity of ſome Times, as in our long Rebellion, this Uſe was Sacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſcontinued, to the Infamy of the Nation, the Diſhonour of God, and the Detriment of his Church in theſe Kingdoms. And no wonder, that ſuch an unheard of way of Reformation, <hi>by melting of Organ Pipes into Bullets, and pulling down of Churches,</hi> ſhould be by ſuch Pretenders to Religion, who not only diſcountenanced all Decency in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip; but deſtroyed that Worſhip it ſelf, ſo far as it was promoted by the Publick Exerciſe of our incomparable Liturgy, the <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> the Lord's Prayer, the Creed and the Decalogue; all which remarkably ſuffered an Eclipſe together.</p>
            <p>And it's but fitting now, That ſince the memory of the Profaneneſs, Irreligion and Sacriledge of thoſe Days is ſo offenſive, and has been ſo long a Scandal to us, we ſhould endeavour to blot out a part of the remaining <hi>Odium,</hi> by Reſtoring this ancient Uſe in our Churches, which we have ſo much Reaſon, Religion, and Authority for.</p>
            <p>And if now, the Judgment of Antiquity, the Uſe of this among the Jews, God's own Appointment of it by his Prophets,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 29.25.</note> and the Scriptures of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> no where forbidding it, or ſuppoſing it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49134:13"/>to be only a Temporal Command, though only from the Severity of the Churches Perſecution it was ſometime diſcontinued; but afterwards it flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again, in the Chriſtian Church, when that did; And in the Nature of the Thing it be of perpetual Uſe, and in the Opinion of the moſt Learned and Pious Men, of a very good one, be not ſufficient Arguments to juſtifie its Lawfulneſs, nothing will. I am ſure nothing can prove it unlawful.</p>
            <p>§ 5. But perhaps, what will be of greater Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with many among us, to Confirm the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of this, beyond all which has been hitherto ſaid, will be the Opinion of ſome Eminent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, who have ſeparated from us, as particularly Mr. <hi>Baxter, and the Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> which I ſhall mention before I diſmiſs this Particular, that you may ſee, How much they agree with us in this Matter.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Five Diſputations,</hi> gives his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Church-Muſick in theſe very words: <q>As for Organs,<note place="margin">P. 112.</note> or other Inſtruments of Muſick (ſays he) in God's Worſhip, they being a Help, partly Natural and partly Artificial, to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilerating of the Spirits for the Praiſe of God, I know no Argument to prove them ſimply Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but what would prove a Cup of Wine unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or the Tune and Metre and Melody of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unlawful.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And more largely does he deliver himſelf in theſe <hi>Five Arguments</hi> in his <hi>Caſes of Conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> 127</note> annexed to his <hi>Chriſtian Directory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49134:14"/>
            <p n="1">As 1. <q>God ſet it up long after <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Law, by <hi>David, Solomon,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="*" place="margin">No bad Precedents in Devotion. 1 Sam. 18.6. 1 Chro. 15.16. 2 Chron. 5.13. &amp; 7.6. &amp; 23.13. Pſal. 98. &amp; 150.</note>.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>It is not an Inſtituted Ceremony meerly, but a Natural Help to the Mind's alacrity: And it is a Duty, and not a Sin, to uſe the Helps of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Lawful Art, though not to Inſtitue Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of our own. As it is lawful to uſe the comfortable Helps of Spectacles in Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bible, ſo is it of Muſick to Exhilerate the Soul towards God.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <q>Jeſus Chriſt joyned with the Jews that uſed it, and never ſpake a word againſt it.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <q>No Scripture forbid deth it, therefore it is not unlawful.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <q>Nothing can be againſt it, that I know of, but what is ſaid againſt Tunes and Melody of Voice. For whereas they ſay, That it is a Human Invention: ſo are our Tunes (and Metre and Verſion) yea, it is not a Human Invention; as the laſt <hi>Pſalm</hi> and many other ſhew, which call us to <hi>Praiſe the Lord with Inſtruments of Muſick.</hi> —And whereas ſome ſay, That they find it do them harm; ſo others ſay of Melodious Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but, as wiſe Men ſay, they find it do them good. And why ſhould the Experience of ſome prejudiced ſelf-conceited Perſon, or of a half-man that knoweth not what Melody is, be ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Experience of all others, and deprive them of all ſuch Helps and Mercies, as theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſay they find no benefit by.</q>—More to this effect he adds in Juſtification of the Lawfulneſs of Muſick in the Service of God.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49134:14"/>
            <p>To this Opinion of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s, I ſhall add that of the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> very different from thoſe of <hi>Geneva</hi> on this laſt <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>He (ſay they, ſpeaking of <hi>David</hi>) exhorteth them, that they might Praiſe God the better, to ſtir up their Joy with Muſical Inſtruments<note n="*" place="margin">'Tis to be noted, That the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> refer the meaning of this <hi>Pſalm</hi> to thoſe two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. where they farther ſay, It ſeemeth moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that by Pſalms, he means the <hi>Pſalms of David</hi> ſet to the Harp or Pſaltery; by Hymns, certain Ditties made upon ſpecial occaſions; and by Spiritual Songs, ſuch as were not Compoſed before hand, and Prickt before them with Muſical Notes, but ſuch as men endited by an extraordinary Gift. — And <hi>Mr. Pool</hi>'s <hi>Annot.</hi> on <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Most take Pſalms to be ſuch as anciently were ſung with Muſical Inſtruments.</hi>
                  </note>.</q> And, <hi>The Remark upon it is unanſwerable,</hi> If Muſical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments (as is granted) had that Power then, how have they changed their Nature ſince?</p>
            <p>Theſe Authorities are great enough, I hope, to balance any thing can be ſaid, by any of the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to the contrary. But I ſhall ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more in Juſtification of the Lawfulneſs of this, when I come in the Third Place to Anſwer the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt it.</p>
            <p>Having ſpoken thus much concerning the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of Church-Muſick, which was the Firſt and Chief Thing to be done.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> I proceed in the Second Place, to ſhew the great Uſe and Advantages of it.</p>
            <p>And Theſe are ſo many, that 'tis an hard matter not to be long, if not tedious in their Enlargement. But, for my more Regular proceeding, I ſhall reduce them to theſe Five Heads.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49134:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. It will Regulate the untunable Voices of the Multitude, and make the Singing in the Church more orderly and harmonious.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It will ſtir up the Affections of Men, and make them the fitter for Devotion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It will compoſe their Thoughts, and drive away Evil Suggeſtions from their Minds.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It will prepare them for the being better Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Divine Service they are about.</p>
            <p n="last">Laſtly, It will make the whole Service of God be the more Solemn and Auguſt, and the People more Serious and Reverential, when they are at it; and more Silent and Grave at their coming in, or going out of the Church.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of the chief Uſes of the Organ which my Meditations ſuggeſt, and of them briefly in their order.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Then the Organ will Regulate the untune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Voices of the Multitude, and make the Singing in the Church more orderly and harmonious. It cannot be ſuppoſed, but there will be great Diſcord and Jarrings in a mixed Company of Singers, where few perhaps have had the Benefit of Art to tune and help their Voices. And where there is ſuch, Confuſion and Diſorder will naturally follow, which ſhould not be permitted in the Praiſes of God, if it may be avoided: For we are to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <hi>to make his Praiſe glorious;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.2.</note> and to ſet it forth after the beſt manner we can. <hi>Praiſe ſhould be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in wiſdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>and the Lord will proſper it,</hi> ſays
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49134:15"/>the wiſe Son of <hi>Syrach.</hi> It being ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to ſuppoſe, God will be delighted with ſuch unpleaſant and harſh Tones in his Service, as Men in their common Diverſion would not endure. They ſeek to Accompliſh themſelves by the Help of Art to ſing well and regularly, to pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and hearers.</p>
            <p>And think ye, when they ſing to God, it be no matter, whether they ſing well or not? They are to pay him the beſt Services; and in this Caſe the beſt are the ſweeteſt, and moſt harmonious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, when their Hearts and their Voices are kept in the beſt Tune, as they will be with the help of an Organ, which is therefore to be allowed as moſt uſeful; this being the only ſort of Muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which is able to do ſo, having ſuch a Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Loudneſs, and decent Modulation going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it, as will keep all in, and at the ſame time, both grace the Service, and pleaſe the Offerer.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) It will ſtir up the Affections of the Soul, and make them the fitter for Devotion.</p>
            <p>There are very few Men of ſuch ſprightly and ardent Minds towards the Service of God, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they will want a little quickning and ſtirring up to keep the regular and intent in the Duty they are about. And, as for the generality of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they are flat and dull, and too liſtleſs about ſuch a weighty Buſineſs. And therefore, if this Indiſpoſition can be rectified by the help of ſuch a Muſical Inſtrument, as in all probability it will, ſince 'tis its Nature thus apparently to excite and raiſe Mens Affections, we muſt conclude it to be a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Advantage to Religion.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49134:16"/>
            <p>And that it will do ſo, we have two very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Inſtances in the Scripture for the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Confirmation of it: Both taken from that known practice of the Prophets in the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> who, for the promoting of the Spirit of Prophecy within them, and the better raiſing their Intention towards God at that time, they called for the Muſicians to play before them. The one, and the cleareſt of the two, is that 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3. where when <hi>Jehoram</hi> and <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> made their joynt Importunity to <hi>Eliſha</hi> to get them Water, for want of which their Hoſts were greatly diſtreſſed;<note place="margin">2 Kings 3.15, 16, 17.</note> he bid them bring him a Minſtrel. <hi>And it came to paſs, when the Minſtrel play'd, the Hand of the Lord came upon him: And he ſaid, Thus ſaith the Lord, make this Valley full of Diches,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It ſhall be filled with Water, that ye may drink,</hi> &amp;c. The other Inſtance is that 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.5. when the Spirit of the Lord was to come upon <hi>Saul,</hi> to make him a Prophet, and to ſtir up the ſame Spirit in thoſe Old Prophets who were ſent to his Ordination, that they might Prophecy together, 'tis ſaid,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.5.</note> 
               <hi>The Company of Prophets came down from the High Place, with a Pſaltery, and a Tabret, and a Pipe, and an Harp before them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In both which places, 'tis obſervable, That 'twas nothing but Inſtrumental Muſick, which was made uſe of in thoſe Caſes, to awaken their Souls, and to ſtir up the Spirit of Prophecy in them. And from thence I argue <hi>A Fortiori,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of Muſick uſed in the Schools of the Prophets, <hi>vide</hi> Bp. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteet</hi>'s <hi>Orig. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4. § 6, 7</note> If theſe were able to ſtir up the inſpired Principles of their Souls, for ſuch a mighty Thing, as the Conveying the Prophetick Spirit into another, among the Jews; certainly they may well be concluded proper and uſeful for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49134:16"/>the ſtirring up the Spirit of Prayer, and to move the Affections of the Soul, that they may be the ſitter for the Worſhip of God, in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>I may well here ſubjoyn, what I find by many quoted concerning the regulating and ſweetning, as well as ſtirring up of the Affections of the Heart towards God by this means; inſomuch, that it will delight in Sorrow as well as Joy, and make a Man chearful, even in his Lamentation and Mourning for his Sins, and when he is doing the ſevereſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances for them. The Reaſon whereof is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently well ſet forth by our <hi>Judicious</hi> Mr. <hi>Hook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. Pol. lib. 5. § 38.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <p>Touching Muſical Harmony, (ſays he) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Inſtrument or by Voice, it being but of High and Low in Sounds a due proportionable diſpoſition, ſuch notwithſtanding is the Force thereof, and ſo pleaſing Effects it hath, in that very Part of Man which is moſt Divine, that ſome have been thereby induced to think, That the Soul it ſelf by Nature is, or hath in it Harmony.</p>
                  <p>A Thing which delighteth all Ages, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemeth all States; a Thing as ſeaſonable in Grief as in Joy; as decent, being added unto Actions of greateſt Weight and Solemnity, as being uſed when Men ſequeſtred themſelves from Action. The Reaſon hereof is an admirable Facility which Muſick hath to expreſs and repreſent to the Mind, more inwardly than any other ſenſible Mean, the very ſtanding, riſing and falling; the very ſteps and inflections every way, the turns and varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of all Paſſions, whereunto the Mind is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49134:17"/>yea, ſo to imitate them, that whether it reſemble unto us the ſame ſtate wherein our Minds already are, or a clean contrary, we are not more contentedly by the one confirmed, than changed and led away by the other.</p>
               </q> And ſo on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that excellent Man.</p>
            <p>So that you ſee the admirable Uſe of Muſick to regulate the Affections, as well as to move them in our Devotion.</p>
            <p>I might here mention what wonderful Effects may be found in Prophane Authors concerning the Powers of Muſick, as the Learned <hi>Caſaubon</hi> and <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> have obſerved. We are told of a famous Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, who by Playing on his Inſtrument, could work up <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> to ſuch a ſit of Rage, as to force him, with great fury and wrath, to graſp his Sword, ready for any Combat: and then again, by a curious turn of Art, preſently be able to allay that Paſſion, and produce in him the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Effects of Gentleneſs and Mildneſs. The <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians,</hi> a moſt obſtinate ſort of People,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> of Muſick.</note> when divided among themſelves, and at Variance even to a Civil War, were directed by the Oracle to hear the famous <hi>Terpander</hi> play upon his Harp, which, when they had done, they made up the Difference with Tears in their Eyes, and embracing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, returned Friends. <hi>Homer</hi> introduces <hi>Achilles</hi> in the height of his Fury towards <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Muſick<note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Greeks</hi> were careful to teach their Children Muſick, deeming it requiſite, by the Aſſiſtance thereof, to Form and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Minds of Youth to what was decent, ſober and vertuous; believing the Uſe of Muſick beneficially efficacious to incite to all ſerious Actions, <hi>&amp;c. Ibid.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49134:17"/>
            <p>We are told alſo, That<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Grotius in</hi> 1 Sam. 10.5.</note> 
               <hi>Pythagoras</hi> did mollifie ſierce Minds by Muſick. That <hi>Aſclepiades</hi> did ſtop the Rage of Sedition. <hi>Damon</hi> reduc'd Petulant and Debauched young Men to Modeſty and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety. And <hi>Xenocrates</hi> cure Mad-men by the ſame means.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall leave theſe, hoping we have no ſuch to try the Experiment upon, and proceed</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) To another Uſe of Church-Muſick, and particularly of the <hi>Organ, viz.</hi> That it will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Men's Thoughts, and drive away Evil Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions from their Minds at their Devotion. The Devil be ſure is then moſt buſie to ply his Miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Suggeſtions, and to endeavour the diſcompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Men's Minds, when at their Devotion they are ſeeking the Ruin of his Kingdom. Then it is, That he often injects Evil Imaginations before us; and tempts us, by raiſing inordinate Paſſions in our Hearts, and tries to make us wander from the great Buſineſs we are about.</p>
            <p>But then, the ſeaſonableneſs of Muſick will help to recall our Minds, and keep them from ſuch a Roving and Wandring away from it. It will be a means to keep them from evil Objects, and from the ſly and malignant Inſinuations of Evil Angels, which Repreſent them to our Minds. It will tend much to rid theſe,<note place="margin">Just. Mart. Queſt. <hi>107.</hi>
               </note> of all thoſe ſad and gloomy and melancholy and luſtful Imaginations, which may diſturb and diſcompoſe them. It will diſpel thoſe Clouds which make them heavy and dull. It will diſcharge thoſe irregular Paſſions, which do tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vex them; and keep the Heart from being fretted with anxious Thoughts and racking Fears
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49134:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49134:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49134:19"/>and diſtracting Doubts, which at that time may lye heavy upon them, and bring it in ſuch a ſedate and even Temper, as is beſt for Divine Contemplation and Prayer.</p>
            <p>Muſick will bring the Soul into ſuch an Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Order, as will make it ever enjoy a pleaſant ſtate of Peace and Tranquility. The Reflections it will prompt it to make, on all that is good and great; and the Meditations it will Exalt in us, of the wonderful Works of the Creation and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the Happineſs is laid up in ſtore for good People, will always <hi>make glad the City of God, the Tabernacle of the most Higheſt,</hi> which the Soul of Man may be ſaid to be: And whatſoever does ſo, will be a Torment and Vexation to thoſe Evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits<note n="*" place="margin">Doemones fugat Depellit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> who ſeek her Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Hence we may take up a Saying, which is father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon <hi>Luther; Scimus Muſicam Doemonibus etiam inviſam &amp; intolerabilem eſſe:</hi> That the Devils can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure, but perfectly hate Muſick. And we have reaſon to believe it, becauſe there is no ſuch thing in Hell; but the oppoſite to that, <hi>viz. weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and wailing, and gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi> Quite op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Repreſentation of the ſtate of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Kingdom of Heaven, where is Singing and Rejoycing and Gladneſs. And to fit our ſelves for their Society, in the glorious Preſence of God, we muſt have our Minds calm'd, our Paſſions ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, and our Souls tempered with the Precepts of Religion, for the ſurer Reception of which, will the Charms of Muſick give a great Preparation. And</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49134:19"/>
            <p n="4">(4.) This is another Uſe and Advantage of it; It will prepare us for the being better Edified in our Divine Service. For, when our Affections are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Raiſed, our Thoughts Compoſed, and our Minds made Sedate and Calm, as we have ſeen, then ſhall we be in the fitteſt Diſpoſition, the more ſeriouſly to attend upon, and the more eagerly bent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch Divine Inſtructions, as ſhall in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Service, be offered to our Underſtanding. The Soul will then be qualified to take the beſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions; the Head and the Heart will be enliven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the Ears and Eyes will be opened, through thoſe moſt ſweet and charming Sounds, whereby the Treaſure of Goods Things will be convey'd into the Mind, and take the deeper Root in us; and ſo the whole Man will be Edified in the Precepts of Religion.</p>
            <p>Thus Inſtrumental is Muſick to make us moſt Knowing, as well as moſt Devout. Our Reaſon too, will reap a great Benefit by it, and we ſhall become the more Rational, and have a clearer inſight into the Things above, by being awakened thereto, in the Service of God, <hi>with ſtringed Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Organs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The pleaſing Force of which is ſo irreſiſtable, that Men muſt do Violence to their Natural Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers (unleſs they are monſtrouſly bad) to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it: This being ſo artificially fitted, as will make at the ſame Time a curious Addreſs, as well to the Judgment as the Imagination, and muſt capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate both, unleſs ſo dull and ſtupid, as to be beneath the Capacity of<note n="*" place="margin">The Muſick of <hi>Orpheus</hi> and <hi>Amphion,</hi> had influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Fiſhes and Beaſts. Sir <hi>William Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>'s fourth <hi>Eſſay upon Poetry.</hi> The Powers of Muſick (ſays he) are either felt or known by all men, and are allowed to work ſtrangely upon the Mind and the Body, the Paſſions and the Blood, to raiſe Joy and Grief, to give Pleaſure and Pain, to cure Diſeaſes, and the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Sting of the <hi>Tarantula,</hi> to give motions to the Feet, as well as the Heart, to compoſe diſturbed Thoughts, to aſſiſt and heighten Devotion it ſelf, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 288. The <hi>Tarantula</hi> is a moſt venomous Spider, ſome ſay a Fly, ſo called from <hi>Tarantum,</hi> a <hi>Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> City, where they moſt abound, whoſe Sting is deadly, yet curable by divers Sounds of Muſick, <hi>Sand</hi>'s <hi>Travels, fol.</hi> 249. I appeal to the Experience of Diſſenters, whether they are not much affected, and think themſelves edified with the pleaſing Tone and Cadencies and Elevations of the Voice of their Preachers? and then, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they might not be aſſiſted with the ſweeter Sounds of Muſical Inſtruments?</note> Bruits.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49134:20"/>
            <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> among his Confeſſions which he makes to God in ſeveral Books, ſays, ſpeaking of Church-Muſick,<note place="margin">Quantum fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi in Hymnis &amp; Canticis tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, ſuave ſonan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Eccleſiae tuae vocibus commotus acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Voces il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae influebant Auribus meis, &amp; eliquabatur Veritas tua in Cor meam, &amp; ex eâ, Aeſtuebat inde affectus Pietatis, &amp; currebant Lacrymae, &amp; bene mihi erat cum eis. <hi>Aug. Confeſ. lib. 9. in Calce cap. 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>How much did I weep at thy Hymns and Songs, being vehemently moved with the Voices of thy Melodious Church. Thoſe Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces did flow in at my Ears, and thy Truth was melted into mine Heart, and from thence boiled up ſuch an Affection of Piety, as did make my Tears to run down, and then it was well with me, becauſe of them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems he was ſo affected therewith, that he ſhed Tears in token of a Religious Joy, when his Ears were delighted with the Voices which ſung forth the Praiſes of God, and his Heart Inſtructed in the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of them. And notwithſtanding, he ſeems to be afraid of being carried away with the former to the hurt and prejudice of the latter: yet he was forced to acknowledge, the great Profit the Church did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by ſuch a Cuſtom, ſo fit for Edification<note n="*" place="margin">Confeſ. l. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Particular with the words of St. <hi>Baſil</hi> to this effect,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl. Pol. l.</hi> 5. § 38. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> as I find them Tranſlated by our <hi>Judicious</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <p>Whereas (ſays he) the Holy Spirit ſaw that Mankind is unto Vertue
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49134:20"/>hardly drawn, and that Righteouſneſs is the leaſt accounted of, by reaſon of the proneneſs of our Affections to that which delighteth. It pleaſed the Wiſdom of the ſame Spirit to borrow from Melody that Pleaſure, which mingled with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Myſteries, cauſeth the ſmoothneſs and ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that which toucheth the Ear, to convey as it were by ſtealth the Treaſure of Good Things into Man's Mind. To this purpoſe were thoſe Harmonious Tunes and Pſalms deviſed for us, that they which are either in years but young, or touching Perfection of Vertue, as yet not grown to ripeneſs, might, when they think they ſing, Learn.</p>
                  <p>O the wiſe Conceit of that Heavenly Teacher, which hath by his Skill found out a way, that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Things, wherein we delight, we may alſo learn that whereby we profit!</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus advantageous does the Uſe of Church-Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick appear to be, to prepare us the better for Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in the Divine Service.</p>
            <p>(5ly. and Laſtly) I come now in the laſt place to ſhew, That the Organ will make the whole Service of God be the more Solemn and Auguſt, and the People more ſerious and Reverential when they are at it; and more Silent and Grave at their coming in or going out of the Church.</p>
            <p>There is, beſides at the ſeveral Times when the <hi>Pſalms</hi> are ſung, ſome other proper Tunes cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily made uſe of for the Organ to play ſome taking Leſſon or decent Floriſh or other by it ſelf, which goes by the Name of <hi>Voluntaries;</hi> and is chiefly to anſwer this laſt Uſe and Advantage of it.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49134:21"/>
            <p>This ſort of Muſick, is either made juſt before the Service begins, which ſeems a very proper time for it, to engage the Congregation to a ſerious Thoughtfulneſs, and to a civil Deportment and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, when they are taking their Places, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to enter upon the moſt Solemn Acts of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Worſhip of God. Or it is alſo uſed at the end of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> before the Leſſons be read, to ſtrike a reverential awe upon our Spirits, and to melt us into a fit Temper to receive the beſt Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from the Word of God. And it is contrived as a new Ornament and Grace to carry us through the whole Service with Seriouſneſs and Devout At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, with Alacrity, Sobriety and Peace. Or laſtly, It is uſed at the end of the whole, to take off ſome little whiſpering Diſturbances,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cork</hi>'s Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Singing, Cap. 3.</note> through the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of ſome People, and to drown that ungrateful ruſhing Murmur and Noiſe which the ſtirring of ſo many People together, at that time of going out of the Church, muſt occaſion.</p>
            <p>It being well provided and deſigned by the Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Prudence of our Governours, to let nothing there be heard in the Houſe of God, but what is grateful and becoming that holy Place. And eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially during the Time of Divine Service, all Things ſhould be performed with as great Silence and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence as is poſſible. Nothing is then to be heard but the Word of God, and the Voice of humble Supplicants; the Prayers of the Devout, and the Praiſes of ſuch as be joyful in the Lord.</p>
            <p>And therefore by the way, the indecent Noiſe which is too often made by the opening and clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping faſt of Pew-doors (a reaſon why anciently Seats in the Church had no Doors to them) and the nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeous
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49134:21"/>Rawkings, and unneceſſary Coughing and Spitting, which are made by the People, though little regarded, come within the Cenſure of a Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, and may doubtleſs in a great meaſure be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, if they be not at that time very much indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed for Civility as well as Devotion.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhewn, and I hope in ſome meaſure proved, The Uſe and Advantages, as well as the Lawfulneſs of Organs in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>It remains now that we make our ſincere and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Attendance to the Performance of our Duty in this beſt part of it eſtabliſhed among us, where our Devotion being raiſed with the additional help of Muſical Inſtruments, we may beſt acquaint our ſelves with the Excellency of our Service, and the Advantages of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> But there remains ſtill another Particular to be diſcourſed in the Third place, that imports the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the Objections, and, if poſſible, removing the Prejudices, which the Adverſaries of Church-Muſick, have againſt this Practice. And if this be not done, in vain will the Arguments prove which ſet forth the Uſe and Advantages of this Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I confeſs the former are more eaſily anſwered, than the latter taken away; however, having gone ſo far, I ſhall now briefly make an Attempt on both, and pray for Succeſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> The Principal Objection I ſhall begin with, which is brought againſt this Cuſtom and Practice of our Church, is, <hi>That it is a Jewiſh Ceremony, and an Appointment of the Law, but was to be aboliſhed in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49134:22"/>the Chriſtian Church. That, though it might ſuit well enough with that Infant State: yet now by the Coming of Christ, it is to be done away, as the other Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Law are.</hi> This is the utmoſt force of the Objection, as warranted by the <hi>Geneva</hi> Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> expreſly ſpeaking to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p>And 'tis great pity ſuch pernicious Annotations ſhould be ſuffered to be printed with the Bible, ſo contrary in many places, to the ſenſe and meaning of it. But for Anſwer to this Objection, which is very peremptorily made without any offer of proof to juſtifie it,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>1</label> I ſay Firſt, That the Inſtitution of Muſical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in the Service of God, was never a part of the Ceremonial Law, neither was it appointed or preſcribed by the Law; and for that Reaſon, the uſe thereof, as of other Ceremonies, was not to be done away at the Coming of Chriſt. And now to ſhew, That 'twas no part of the Ceremonial Law, is very manifeſt for theſe two Reaſons. 1. Becauſe they were in uſe before that Law was given. And, 2. They were not eſtabliſhed any where by the Law, nor till above Five hundred years after the Ratifying and Sealing of it up.</p>
            <p>As to the former, Their being in Uſe before the Law, appears, in that <hi>Miriam the Propheteſs</hi> celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> with the Ceremony of Muſical Inſtruments, on that Religious Account,<note place="margin">Exod. 15.20.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20. And ſo likewiſe, they might be uſed on other ſuch like occaſions, as they were <hi>when</hi> Saul <hi>was made a Prophet;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.5.</note> which was before the Inſtitution of theſe, though long after the Time of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49134:22"/>
            <p>In ſhort then, The Ceremonial Law was given and compleatly ratified by <hi>Moſes:</hi> But we cannot find any where that he gives an Inſtitution to theſe Things;<note place="margin">Except the Trumpet for the Calling of Aſſemblies, &amp;c. <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.</note> Inſtruments of Muſick were not appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Divine Service in his Time, though poſſibly they might be uſed then by others, as well as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, in Anſwer to the latter, it is plain, That they were an Inſtitution of <hi>David</hi>'s in his moſt flouriſhing ſtate; and the firſt time we read of their Eſtabliſhment, is, at his welcoming home of the Ark from the <hi>Philiſtines:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chro. 15.16.</note> 
               <hi>And</hi> David <hi>ſpake to the chief of the Levites, to appoint their Brethren to be Singers with Inſtruments of Muſick, Pſalteries, and Harps and Cymbals ſounding, by lifting up the Voice with Joy.</hi> According to which, this, afterwards went by the Name of <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Commandment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 29.25.</note> 
               <hi>and the Commandment of the Lord by his Prophets.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a very remarkable occaſion it was ſo called, when good King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> reſtored this Cuſtom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,<note place="margin">Ezra 3.10.</note> which in the Reign of ſome evil Kings had been neglected.</p>
            <p>From both which places, it appearing to be of <hi>David</hi>'s Inſtitution, could not be a part of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Law, which was compleated before by <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 12.32. in theſe words (after he had bid <hi>Iſrael</hi> hearken unto the Statutes and unto the Judgments which he was to teach them — he ſays) <hi>What thing ſoever I command you, obſerve to do it: Thou ſhalt not add thereto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 12.32.</note> 
               <hi>nor diminiſh from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>2</label> I Anſwer in the Second Place, That if this Uſe of Inſtrumental Muſick was a part of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49134:23"/>Law, and to be done away in Chriſt; it would have been as thoſe other Typical Things were, a Shadow of ſomewhat to come, which was to be done away by the Coming of that Subſtance; but no ſuch thing being to be made appear, we may rationally conclude, this is not to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way under the Goſpel. But the ſame Reaſon for its firſt Inſtitution, will always hold good, as long as People have dull and irregular Affections to be ſtirred up, and raiſed fit for to ſupply. And 'tis as proper now in the Chriſtian Church, to ſtir up Mens Minds, to compoſe their Thoughts, and to inflame their Devotion therewith, as it was in the Reign of <hi>David,</hi> and therefore as reaſonable that it ſhould be continued.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> It is again objected againſt this Cuſtom, <hi>That 'tis not ſo edifying in the Chriſtian Church, as we plead for; nor ſo proper, where we are not to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, with External Ceremonies, and the outward Formality of Serving him, as the Jews did; but</hi> in Spirit and in Truth.<note place="margin">John 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>And for this Reaſon Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Muſick ought to be aboliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> Sol.To which I Anſwer, That it is no way Repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the moſt Spiritual Worſhip whatſoever: But ſo far from being prejudicial to it, that 'tis highly advantageous to make the Chriſtian Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the more Spiritual, and to ſtir up the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Soul in order thereunto; and by means of it, to make us the more ſtedfaſtly and devout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>cleave unto the Lord;</hi> and the more Attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to heed the Things that are ſpoken in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49134:23"/>for our better Edification, which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewn. And the Experience of thoſe, who have profeſſed ſeriouſly to have received great Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by it, is a farther Argument to convince us of its Uſe; which, when we have Experienced likewiſe, will, I hope, oblige us to make the ſame Acknowledgment.</p>
            <p>There be ſome other Objections among us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Thing, of leſſer Note, which ſcarce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ſerious Anſwer. Some ſay, <hi>They don't like it, and they ſhall never endure it.</hi> Well, it may be ſo; but then it muſt argue the want of Prudence in them, and Reſpect to their own Credit, in not concealing that Diſlike, becauſe of the mean Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Men commonly have of ſuch<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aſinus ad Lyram.</hi> Fab. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopi, &amp;c. 414. By Sir <hi>R. L.</hi>
               </note> Creatures as do not love Muſick.</p>
            <p>Such a Diſlike argues a moroſe, ſowre, and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd Diſpoſition, or elſe a ſtupid, dull and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Temper, and that in no ſmall degree neither. Otherwiſe, ſo harmonious and piercing a Thing as that, which is ſo every way adapted to accoſt and captivate with pleaſure, the Affections of a well compoſed Soul, muſt of neceſſity move it to a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and a loving of it<note n="†" place="margin">They muſt have hearts very dry and tough, ſays Mr. <hi>Hooker, Eccl. Pol. l.</hi> 5. § 38. And ſure he is of a rugged temper, and hath an ill compoſed Soul, who feels not theſe Effects (meaning of calm'd Souls, raiſed Affections, and mollified Hearts, by means) of that grave and pleaſant Harmony which doth accompany this Office; and we may fear he is not of <hi>David</hi>'s Spirit, whoſe Ears are offended, whoſe Spirit is diſturbed, or his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion hindered by Vocal or Inſtrumental Muſick, ſays Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s <hi>Companion to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> Part I. Sect. 8. § 2. Whoever find themſelves wholly inſenſible to theſe Charms, would, I think, do well to keep their own Counſel, for fear of Reproaching their own Temper, and bringing the Goodneſs of their Natures, if not of their Underſtandings into queſtion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sir <hi>William Temple</hi>'s <hi>Eſſay of Poetry</hi> at the very end, <hi>p.</hi> 340.</note> 
               <q>This being wrought (as <hi>Boetius</hi> acquaints us) through the anſwerable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Notes in Muſick to thoſe in Nature.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49134:24"/>
            <p>But however, if ſome People cannot conceal the preſent bent of their particular Diſaffections, and the Diſſonancy of an ill Temper, yet how do they know they ſhall never like this Thing?</p>
            <p>To ſay ſo, does farther Argue a great Obſtinacy and Perverſneſs of Mind in them; and that they ſay, They cannot, when in truth They will not. Certainly, nothing but an invincible Ignorance can Excuſe them in ſuch a Saying, becauſe 'tis plain there is no ſuch an impoſſibility in the Thing, but all People may like it, if they will. And to ſpeak ſo for the future, <hi>That they never ſhall,</hi> ſhews a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Spirit of Perverſneſs, That having too much Cauſe to know the Inflexibility and Stubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their own Natural Tempers, they believe they ſhall never be able to poliſh and amend them; and by all their Endeavours to make their Paſſions obey their Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But to regulate theſe, I muſt preſcribe Church-Muſick as the beſt means; and if Mens Prejudices againſt the Service of our Church, be not too great and unreaſonable, which is moſt to be feared, That being duly and devoutly attended to, will in all probability effect the Cure.</p>
            <p>So ſhall we be brought to live as Brethren, Converſe as Neighbours, and go up to the Houſe of God as Friends; there joyntly to partake of the great Bleſſings and Benefits of our <hi>Excellent Service.</hi> On which, it ſhall ſuffice at preſent to Remark, That though there be great Harmony and Sweetneſs in our Church-Muſick, yet none comparable to that in the <hi>Liturgy</hi> it ſelf. So,</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49134:24"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> I come now in the laſt place, To conclude the whole, with an Exhortation to you, to ſtick hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily and devoutly to the Performance of that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Church Service of ours Eſtabliſhed among us, as being the beſt and fitteſt of any in the whole Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian World, to anſwer the Ends of our Holy Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely, to give us a peaceable and happy Life here, and to bring us to Heaven hereafter.</p>
            <p>This Laſt is the great. End we are all to Aim at, and That the beſt Means to direct our Aim and to carry us thither. A Church we have the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be Members of, which for the Soundneſs of its Doctrine, and Regularity of its Worſhip, is the Beauty of Chriſtendom, and the Glory of the Reformation.</p>
            <p>The Value of whoſe Diſcipline is only leſſened for want of a ſtricter Execution, and That, though moderate in it ſelf, if raiſed to its Primitive Uſage, would be thought too rigorous and ſevere, and not well able to comport with the Difficulty of the Times, to ſolve a preſent Exigence.</p>
            <p>But take the whole Conſtitution of our Church, as it ſtands, The Envy of our Neighbours, the great Bulwark againſt the Inundations of Hereſie and Schiſm, the Hatred and Fear of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and, I hope, the Rock of Ages, and there is no Compariſon between this and any other Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Chriſtian World: Againſt which, Let neither the Malice of Devils, nor the Policy of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor the Craft of <hi>Geneva,</hi> be ever able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail; either to overthrow its Strength through a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Diviſion among her Members, or to rifle its Beauty, through a Deluge of Vice; or to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49134:25"/>her Foundation by a Treacherous Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Every Alteration in ſo well an ordered. Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will be for the worſe, and give too great an Occaſion for the Triumphs of her Enemies, who would be glad to have her Honour laid in the Duſt.</p>
            <p>This was not long ſince the wiſhed for <hi>Aſylum</hi> of our oppreſſed Neighbours, who would then have thought themſelves the happieſt Chriſtians in the World, if they could but have obtained ſuch an Eſtabliſhment, or but the Favour of her Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but being, even beyond their Expectation, ready to receive them, is not however ſo heartily embraced and ſtuck to, as might well be expected from her, and pretended by many of thoſe who are fled to us for Refuge.</p>
            <p>And I ſpeak it with aſtoniſhment, That they, who thought they could never do or ſpeak enough to promote its Intereſt, and advance its Glory, ſhould hold ſo treacherous a Correſpondence with thoſe who unwarrantably ſeparate from us, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ever be thought to wiſh well to her Peace, when they ſo induſtriouſly ſeek to divide her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis certainly too juſt a Reflection upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of theſe Proteſtant Refugees, to partake of the Protection of the Church, without obeying the Laws of her Communion. Such do but too like the Viper's Brood, eat out the Bowels of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Nouriſhes them up, and Maintains them with Ability to ſupport themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49134:25"/>
            <p>But let us be more Conſiſtent with one another, and with our Chriſtian Duties; and waving all by-Reſpects and ſiniſter ſelfiſh Ends, let us firmly adhere to its Doctrine, Diſcipline and Worſhip: So ſhall we beſt Secure the Proteſtant Religion in General, by Securing this beſt part of it Eſtabliſhed among us: But chiefly hereby ſhall we Secure our League with Heaven, and the Intereſt of our Immortal Souls, far beyond our Temporal Welfare and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, which this however, through the Bleſſing of God, will honeſtly promote, and therefore the more ſecurely help to obtain.</p>
            <p>We have all things that we can deſire to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh Thoſe great Ends; we of this Town particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, have the Daily Sacrifice of Prayer in this Houſe of God; we have with others an Accurate Form of Prayer, containing the moſt proper Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and pious Matter, and ſuitable Expreſſions, fit for our Devotion. We have proper <hi>Pſalms</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to Praiſe God with, and proper Leſſons, and conſtant Sermons to Inſtruct us in our Duty. We have excellent Collects, and a moſt pathetical Litany to ſolicit our Heavenly Father, for the Mercies we want, and to avert the Judgments and Dangers we fear. And now by a kinder Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to our ſelves, than to our Neighbours, we have the moſt proper Means of Inſtrumental Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, to quicken our Hearts, and to raiſe our Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to make us the more Devout.</p>
            <p>All ſo Edifying and Inſtructive, that it muſt be our fault, if we be not conſtantly made the wiſer and better for being here. It behoves us therefore to take care that we be here often, and that our Hearts be full of Faith and Love, of Humility
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49134:26"/>and Devotion when we come, and then we need not doubt of having been heard and accepted when we go away.</p>
            <p>And I muſt remind you, That ſince now we have the beſt Advantages of any Church in the World, we ſhould endeavour to be the beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the World. We muſt be moſt wanting to our ſelves, if we be not; and our Accounts at the laſt, will be required according to the Talents given.</p>
            <p>We may perhaps have the Vanity to imagine, That God will Excuſe us for our well Meaning, though in many Things we come ſhort of our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But let us not deceive our ſelves, and think to mock God, 'Tis only doing of it will make us acceptable.</p>
            <p>Let us then endeavour to be as good Chriſtians as we ought to be, by doing what is required of us; So ſhall we oblige God to dwell among us, and to delight to bleſs us, with what we wiſh, with Health and Happineſs, with Peace and Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but above all with the Security of our Church and Religion, which we are moſt of all to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            <p>For the doing of what is required, is the beſt Sacrifice we can offer unto him. 'Tis by our good Lives, we Praiſe and Engage him moſt. This makes the beſt Muſick in the Ears of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and is the Chief Melody of our Hearts, to which Muſical Inſtruments are purely ſubſervient, as being a proper means to excite our Devotion, to quicken our Minds, and to raiſe our Affections towards him. But all this is to make us the more enflamed in our Love, and more ready in our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49134:26"/>Obedience.<note place="margin">'Tis a ſevere Judgment not to be ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. Ezek. 33.30, 31, 32, 33.</note> It being almoſt impoſſible to know God, and to be lively and devoutly affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, but we muſt be obedient to him. And then, we ſhall love what he loves, and hate what he hates; conſequently we ſhall be more juſt in our Dealings, more upright in our Converſations, and more holy and ſincere towards God and our Neighbour. Every way better fitted to glorifie him in Heaven, when we can in fervent Devotion, be raiſed to glorifie him here, with our cheerful Hearts and vertuous Lives, through the help of Muſical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments.</p>
            <p>It will now Argue a great deal of Arrogance and Singularity in any of us, to ſpeak againſt the Uſe of Theſe, which the generality of Chriſtians, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this Age, but in thoſe that have been purer and better, have approved of, and looked upon, as of ſingular Uſe and Advantage, for thoſe great Ends; and to help us forward in our way to Happineſs, according to the <hi>Primitive way of Worſhip, by Pſalms and Hymns and Spiritual Songs, and making Melody in our Hearts unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely this which is the Entertainment of Angels and juſt Men in their glorified State, ought not to diſguſt any of us, who ſhould endeavour the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt we can to be qualified for their Company, and to bear a part of their happy Employment, which is with conſtant Readineſs and Agility to obey the Will of God, and with Everlaſting Songs of Praiſe to magnifie his ever glorious Name. This we are to begin here, and to perfect with them above in the Quire of Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49134:27"/>
            <p>And I will not detain you any longer at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, from the grateful Harmony which is to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, through the Excellency of our Organ, and the Sweetneſs of ſo many well tuned Voices as joyn in Conſort with it.</p>
            <p>The Art of Singing <hi>Pſalms,</hi> which ſome of you have happily learnt, may not unfitly be reckoned among thoſe that are Divine: and has no leſs than the Holy Ghoſt for its Original, who taught the Patriarchs, the Prophets and the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>to utter the Praiſes of God with a Song.</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo commendable, and ſo religious an Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, as does become the greateſt Perſon, and is not debaſed by the meaneſt; and in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, will not only raiſe your Eſteem, but your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion too.</p>
            <p>By the Grace and Melody of this Vocal and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental Muſick together, I hope <hi>This Congregation</hi> will be kept in a continual Fervor fit for Devotion, and for retaining ſuch Inſtructions from this Place, as may conduce to the making us firſt Sober and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Chriſtians, then happy and glorious Saints.</p>
            <p>The Charms of which may in time melt us into Love, and ſo charitable an Affection, as that we may all ſeek the Good and Welfare of each other. And, I hope, bring the Uſe of Artificial Singing and Divine Anthems again in requeſt, and be both ſtudied and practiſed too, as they were in the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier Times of Chriſtianity, immediately after the ceaſing of that ſort of Inſpiration, in ſinging Pſalms and Hymns, which was then extraordinary, and to ſupply the place of it.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49134:27"/>
            <p>Even as now, ſince the Expiration of ſome other Extraordinary Gifts which were then in the Church, the latter Ages muſt be ſupplyed from Study and Learning, if at all. And the Pretenders now to Preaching and Praying by the Spirit, without theſe, will be altogether as vain, as their <hi>ex tempore</hi> Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can be ſuppoſed to be without the Advantages of Art.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded, if any thing takes us off from that Vanity, and prevents greater Confuſion and Diſcord from the Minds of Men, it will be the Charms of Muſick, which by the Subtlety of its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Inſinuating Sweetneſs of its Sound, will ſtrike deeper into the Heads of ſome, than the cloſeſt Reaſon poſſibly can into their Hearts. It may work out that Malady which firſt diſcompoſe them, and then moves them to diſcompoſe others; and have the ſame effect it had upon <hi>Saul,</hi> in <hi>making them well, and the Evil Spirit depart from them, and they be turned into other Men.</hi> Into Men of calmer Tempers, more Innocent Diſpoſitions, and more Regular Affections.</p>
            <p>It is reported to be the Saying of an Heathen Poet, <hi>That God loves not thoſe which love not Muſick.</hi> An Opinion indeed too Extravagant for a Chriſtian Entertainment. However, we may obſerve this Curſe commonly attends an Immelodius Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That it argues a querulous, humourſom, ill-compoſed and ill-natured Temper, or elſe a very ſowre and melancholy one<note n="*" place="margin">Spiritus San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus non reſidet ſuper hominem maeſlum. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>1 Kings 19.11, 12.</hi>
               </note>: which in the Opinion of the Hebrew Doctors, is quite unfit to entertain the <hi>Shechinah,</hi> or Glorious Preſence of God. Among Minds diſturbed with Paſſion, and polluted Hearts, is not to be found the Divine and Gentle Spirit. Nay,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49134:28"/>we ſuppoſe the Good Angels themſelves will acquit the Guardianſhip of thoſe,<note place="margin">Cavete Scoti!</note> among whom they find ſuch an uneaſie Habitation. While they are moſt Harmonious themſelves, they will like and befriend us moſt, when we are ſo too.</p>
            <p>And if we truly are ſo, nothing will more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to our Peace, Unity and Agreement among each other; But we ſhall be all knit together in one Common Bond of Amity and Friendſhip; in one Communion and Fellowſhip. By this means we ſhall be brought to mind the ſame Thing, to walk in the ſame Way, and at laſt Arrive at the ſame Happineſs and bleſſed Society of Saints and Angels above, from a zealous and devout Imitation of them here; who readily do the will of God in Heaven, and teach us to do the ſame on Earth, if we hope ever to come where they are, and with them to ſing Eternal Praiſes and <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> unto him that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <hi>To which Place God of his infinite Mercy bring us All, through the Merits and Mediation of his Son Jeſus Christ our Lord. To whom with thy ſelf and bleſſed Spirit of Grace, be aſcribed, as is most due, by us and by all the World, all Glory, Power, Might, Majeſty and Dominion from henceforth and for ever.</hi> Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:49134:28"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <head type="sub">It is thought fit here to ſet down the Method of our Proceeding, and the <hi>PROPOSALS</hi> were made, for the Erecting of the <hi>ORGAN</hi> in in our Pariſh Church of <hi>Tiverton</hi> by way of Subſcription, <hi>March 6. 1695.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimis</hi> THE Undertakers do Promiſe all thoſe who ſhall voluntarily Subſcribe to ſo Pious a Work, that they will apply themſelves to the Right Reverend Father in God, the Lord Biſhop of the Dioceſs, for his Approbation of their good Intentions herein; not doubting of his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Concurrence with them, in promoting the Honour of God, and the Benefit of his Church thereby.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They will alſo apply themſelves to the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Dr. <hi>Lake</hi> the Arch-Deacon of <hi>Exon,</hi> for his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, who has already, not only Recommended ſo good a Work, but has kindly offered the Intereſt
<pb facs="tcp:49134:29"/>he has in an Excellent Artiſt, who ſhall be imployed for the making of the ſame with all convenient ſpeed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They do undertake to procure an excellent and well-contrived Organ, of a ſufficient Bigneſs, and with decent and proper Ornaments of Carved Work, anſwerable to the Pariſh Church; and the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Place there is for the Erecting of it over the Skreen in the ſaid Church. And that they will forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with give Directious for the making of the ſame, as ſoon as they ſhall receive ſufficient Subſcriptions from good and piouſly diſpoſed People, for a ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sum of Money, to diſcharge the Expence of the Organ it ſelf, the bringing it down from <hi>London,</hi> and ſetting it up in a decent Gallery to be made for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Subſcribers are to pay into the Hands of one or other of the Undertakers; half the Sum or Sums by them reſpectively Subſcribed at <hi>Lady-day</hi> next; and the other half at <hi>Midſummer</hi> following, or at any other Time or Times, as ſhall be by them appointed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Undertakers do promiſe to ſet up the Names of all ſuch Perſons who ſhall Subſcribe the Sum of Ten ſhillings or upwards, in a decent Table in the Church, there to remain for ever, as a laſting Teſtimony of their being Benefactors to ſo Religious and generous an Undertaking.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, For the better Encouraging of others, who ſhall be well affected to this Undertaking, the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers
<pb facs="tcp:49134:29"/>themſelves, whoſe Names are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, notwithſtanding the great Care and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Expence they will be extraordinarily put to beyond others, do Subſcribe likewiſe the reſpective Sums following, hoping a great many others, who are of Ability, will follow ſo good an Example.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Undertakers are</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Newte</hi> Rector.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roger Chamberlain</hi> Capital Burgeſſe in the Corporation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Arthur Culme</hi> Capital Burgeſſe in the Corporation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcott</hi> Capital Burgeſſe in the Corporation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Burridge</hi> Capital Burgeſſe in the Corporation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Spurway</hi> Aſſiſtant in the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Frost</hi> Aſſiſtant in the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>☞ The Excellent Artiſt, who makes our Organ, is Mr. <hi>Chriſtian Smith,</hi> a very Honeſt and Ingenious Man, and lives in <hi>Hart-ſtreet</hi> nigh <hi>Bloomsbury</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
